welcome everybody to this episode of the
women in technology spotlight today i
have with me jillian augustine with the
data scientists at monday
she's also a speaker at we are
developers
women in data science and also big data
in london
welcome jillian hi hey
so nice to have you with me jillian i
would like our
listeners viewers to get to know you a
little bit better
maybe you could tell me a little bit
about yourself
sure um so my name is jillian
i'm from the uk so
um i've been in i've been living in
vienna since 2013.
um i'm from the uk um and my family is
originally from grenada in the caribbean
so pretty international um journey to
here
um and um
yeah i've been working in data science
now for
um since 2018 um and
it's it's currently pretty fun
uh you have a very international
background as you said what made you
move to
austria sure so um i actually
i did my phd at the vienna bio center so
my phd was in molecular biology
um and the vienna bio center is a really
good phd program
so this was the main reason that i moved
um
that i moved to vienna i was previously
in canada as well briefly so i
studied at mcgill university for my um a
part of my undergrad
um as well but um after being at mcgill
um in montreal for one year which is
great and it's a great city
i decided this time i would probably
stay in europe because everything's a
bit closer together
i think it's so cool that you say that
the
program at the bio center is such a good
one that you actually heard about it in
the uk which
i'm a bit stoked about that because i
myself i have a phd from the university
uh vienna in chemistry and my uh major
was biochemistry
i did then do my phd in theoretical
chemistry but still i
spent a lot of time there so i'm glad
that the reputation
of the institute is still there my
bachelor's was actually
in biochemistry so i see myself more as
a biochemist
than a biologist but um it's kind of in
the middle
that's such an interesting coincidence
because there aren't actually that many
people with the background like ours
yeah no so cool so
which me this means that you were
actually a natural scientist before you
became a woman in i.t
tell me a little bit about your
educational background what schools did
you go to
why did you choose this path what did
you find interesting
um my path is a bit
um i would call it a zigzag almost
so if i i think back to when i first
went to university 2007
i actually started studying dietetics
which is similar to medical nutrition
um and then um during this course
there were some biochemistry courses and
i found that i actually like the
biochemistry courses more than the other
ones
so my first university was coventry
university in the uk
and then i went to leeds university to
study biochemistry
and then after a couple of years i had
the opportunity to
study abroad so i spent a whole year in
at mcgill university in canada
which was a great experience and really
made me want to um to stay abroad
and so there i focus mainly on biology
developmental biology and also
a bit of french as well why not um
and then um after so i
i found out about development biology
when i was there
i really found it interesting so i
so after i finished my bachelor's degree
in leeds i decided to start a phd at the
vienna biocenter
so i initially started in a
group which studied developmental
biology because it's such a fascinating
field
but then this didn't turn out really to
be the best match for me so then i
changed and i decided to go back towards
biochemistry
um so i started my phd again and just
one year later
and um yeah that was in a more
biochemical focus looking at um the
interactions of different
proteins in the cell during different
conditions um
and during that time i
had some introductory courses to r
and um when i think about
how i got into data science
um during my phd i
i must say i watched a lot of really bad
presentations
so ones where maybe someone says oh you
can clearly see
this but the whole audience is
completely lost
so i became really really enthusiastic
about
doing good data visualizations and
telling stories
um using data in a really good way so in
a really clear way
in an understandable way um
and then i think pretty much from there
this was
this was kind of the bridge to
data science because my my passion
really lies in telling stories with data
and learning from data and finding out
what data can
tell us this is wonderful because
i feel this deeply bad presentations and
you know
information being conveyed in a way that
nobody can actually use it
it's a big problem in science and i love
that you took this approach and that
made you look at
uh how to visualize data i think this is
a big
thing data is not information i think
it's just data
and what you do with it makes it
information so
i i understand that this is what
fascinates you making
data accessible and turning it into
information
so when you became a data scientist um
what was your first step after you
and you did your phd yeah so i was
i was very fortunate to um
i applied to the a1 graduate scheme
and i was fortunate enough to get a
place there so i would become an
a1 graduate in ai and data analytics
and this fit because throughout my phd
and
also before that i had been doing data
analysis on
a regular basis so this really
and this p um this graduate program
really allowed me to gain a better
knowledge of business
so what all the different um
abbreviations mean
what is important for stakeholders
and to understand how how data analytics
fits into the wider scheme of the
business
i was not aware that anyone had a
graduate program that's such a cool
thing we have one at vmware 2 and i feel
that
this is such a good way to move into the
workplace from from
education what exactly what kind of data
does or did you work with that e1 was it
more in terms of marketing or was it
more in
product development or what was the
background
so there were two main um
two main projects which i worked on the
first one looked at
um understanding customer satisfaction
so um one widely used metric is the net
promoter score so if you ever get a
recommendation after you you use a
service saying how likely are you to
recommend
this to somebody else this is this is
this score
um so one one main
project that i was working on looked at
the data
from different and from many different
customers
and try to understand what are the
drivers for someone
being likely to recommend the service or
not
and the second um the second one that i
looked at was more
um on the so not on the customer facing
side although it did have effects
naturally for the customers which was
looking at the networks um so trying to
predict the outages
of um different parts of the network and
trying to
um that wasn't only in the initial
stages but trying to
set things up so that conclusions could
be made in the future in terms of
when is a breakage of a cable likely to
happen
where is it likely to happen and and
that was all in the context of then
allowing
um allowing the cables to get repaired
as soon as possible if you have an idea
of where issues might come up okay
that sounds so interesting um did you
also include data from
sensors in in the network or did you
just
take the data of outages and then cable
breakages from the historic data
so in this case it was it was just um
looking at the outages and
looking at um where they were happening
uh when you compare
your work with data in the academic
space and
in a1 was there a difference in in the
way you
data was approached i think that in the
academic space
data is so in the stem
space at least data is way more valued
so um kind of the
you you work to let the data speak for
itself
and what what the data says is the truth
um and you make decisions based on the
data
um whereas i feel um in the
in the corporate space or in the private
sector
there are way more influencing factors
which come into play and way more things
that you have to take into consideration
before you make a decision so i i would
say
in academia the decisions are more
data-driven than
in the corporate world yeah i understand
so
um i feel that that science is more
occupied with going where the data leads
you and
corporate space might be more give me
the data that i need to do what i want
to do
yeah maybe although even even in
academia it can be unfortunate and i
think it's
kind of a reflection of the
circumstances um
sometimes you
it's known that people can pick and
choose the data that they want to
support their theories
but generally i think overall there is
um
there is a much better appreciation for
the value
of data in higher end i want to make a
little bit of a step back
so i was wondering if you have a family
with a background in stem
did they support you what do you have
brothers and sisters maybe who do
something similar or not
um so my sister is an optometrist
so this is also science related
and my my mum was a dental nurse
and then a health service manager
so again in the medical field so we've
always kind of
been on this side of um um
yeah on this side of the balance i would
say and and obviously since your mother
was also
in that she wasn't surprised when you
chose the career because you know i've
talked to other women where the family
was surprised by the choice of opiate
but
i guess that was not the case in your um
i would say um because i initially
started with dietetics which is very
medical
um because i think that was kind of um
what what was known to me so um
kind of when you think of the careers
that you can go for
anything in the hospital i pretty new
was
i i pretty much knew was was accessible
also because
um i lived pretty close to the hospital
and
and my mom worked there so i spent a lot
of time just
in the offices of the hospital um
but it i think after after dietetics
and then when i switch to biochemistry i
think biochemistry is different
because it's not related to a profession
and i do think i was one of the first
people
i know to do some sort of education
which was not specifically
related to a profession um so
i think um my family and when i think of
my family i think of like extended
family
aunts uncles and godparents and so
um they kind of
check in to see if if i'm okay if i if
everything's going okay
um but i wouldn't say they really know
what i'm i'm doing but they
as long as i say i'm okay then it's fine
for them
uh you touched on two really different
things uh see
and very interesting things here because
um one is
is that that was a role that was known
to you
you know nutritionists and i think
that's a very important
thing to look at what kind of
roles are available to us as women or as
even as men you know there's this this
kind of occupations we know
and then there's all this this entire
field where we have never
met anyone seen anyone do it and i think
that's a big
issue because we might have talents that
are in a completely different
field but um i was thinking about this
recently uh because i was writing
a short article and i remembered what
hannibal lecter said in the silence of
the lambs and when he said
how do we begin to covet we covered what
we see
you know so yeah and i think this is a
big thing and and
something i think we might touch on when
we look at the education of
women children what kind of roles we
we offer to them what we show them what
they can do and the other thing is
i'm not sure if it's related to your
caribbean background but for
my family since my i grew up in africa
and my father is from nigeria
it was they also had this this thing
about
um jobs with educations with clear
outcomes like buckthorn
you know those are the things you would
do and i do feel that my father
always wondered what biochemistry
actually was and now
that i'm at mit he doesn't really know
what i'm doing
so yeah pretty much saying
okay um yeah interesting point around
being a role model how did you
experience being a woman
in in i.t especially since it's also not
only a woman in a tea you also went to a
strange country
and then how is this for you in terms of
like generally when we think about role
models we
are thinking about people who are like
us who
have done what we we want to do and then
we can kind of
follow in their footsteps um in that
sense
i i don't have anybody who is my
role model i mean there are many people
who i aspire to in
in various different ways um definitely
and there are many people who i i can
kind of look up
to and think i want to do what they are
doing um
but it's always very intangible still
so i still feel i'm kind of the first
one going the steps
and and seeing what happens
i i can imagine and which gives you the
opportunity to be a role model for
others who come after you which is cool
also
um but it's always more difficult being
the first then i think it takes a
certain kind of character to
to actually do that as from one and very
centered because
you have to be very clear in what you
actually want to achieve
which brings me to my next question what
kind of goals do you have
i mean you enjoy working with data
obviously but do you have anything
in terms of career path that you have as
a goal
um now i kind of
um i kind of have a rule to myself
which is to create a plan but don't
expect things to go to plan
um and i think it's because um
up until my so
in my bachelor's and even before when i
was at
um college and school kind of if you
work hard then
then you get good results coming out um
and then ac it's quite easy to have a
plan of i will do this and then
do this and do this um but then
i think um when i had to restart my phd
um here then i realized like
you can be you can be really good at
what you're doing but sometimes things
just don't go to plan
and then this is why now i
i my goal is to keep enjoying what i'm
doing
i would say so my goal at the moment
i i've been working i've been focusing
my efforts on visualization for
and data analytics in terms of coding
and this kind of thing
i've been focusing on this for at least
four years and i'm still really
enthusiastic about it
um so this is kind of my goal
um but i know i have a range of skills
so
not only on the coding side and
going towards the software development
side but also on the communication side
and and creating links between
businesses
and more technical people who maybe um
cannot express what they want to say so
so well so i i feel like i have a range
of
tools on my belt and at the moment i'm
i'm focusing more on developing my
software
development skills um because this is
where my interest lies right now but i
don't
necessarily have an aim
i just want to keep enjoying what i'm
doing that's cool
um and i think that's an important part
i mean
a job like like yours means that you
have to stay on top of the technology
and the developments and in the field
and all that
and that is easier if you actually enjoy
what you're doing so passion and
enthusiasm for what you do is a big
thing i feel right
yeah definitely yeah so in terms of work
environment
um i since this is women in technology
um do you have a lot of women you work
with or is it more men
what what's it like so in
our team at the moment they're we're
split into
project managers and then data
scientists and i would say
um on the project management side
it's uh strongly women
and i would say on the data scientist
side it's strongly men
so for the first year no not first year
for the first six months when i was
working in my current position
i was the only woman in a data science
role
um and then my my colleague yelana
milosevic joined
and that was very nice um even though we
don't work together but it was still
it was still nice um and also my
boss is a woman as well which i really
appreciate
so um i think it
and she's also a very technical person
as well so
i even though on a daily basis
i never work with technical women
really um it's
nice to know that they are there because
i think the
diversity in teams like this is
important
i tend to agree but i would like to ask
why did you
feel that it is nice for her to come on
board what difference did
you feel um i think
um when
i think when a team is too homogenous
um then um
some some ways can
some ways or beings can be a bit
exclusive rather than inclusive
so i think the more that there are
different
there are clearly different groups of
people together the more
um the more inclusive it can be and this
also goes in the sense
um of in our team we have some people
who are more chatty
and then some people who are more quiet
or prefer to work by themselves
and i i think like if you were if it
were 90
chatty then the quiet person would not
feel so included
if it were 90 quiet then the chatty
person would not feel so
included so i think having having this
um diversity really allows
each um each group of people to feel
more comfortable
that is a very good insight it's not
about having someone who is completely
like you it's about having many
different people so everyone can beat
themselves
themselves i think yeah you put it in
english yeah
um yeah and i feel that you're also
doing a lot to make the
i.t more diverse by giving all these
talks that for example for women
are developed female developers so what
i'm sorry i forgot the name of the group
but women in data science and
and we are developers sorry and yeah
things like that
um what made you start doing these
things
i think i
like during my phd time we
we had this thing called um uh monday
seminar
where once a year you would have to
present your results to
the rest of the campus and then this
really
gave me practice in presenting things
and
telling stories and um
i suppose because i because
i've been in the audience so many times
and really
just being completely lost and
so it's really important for me that
presentations are good
um good and they are understandable so
um
this is why i also like to do them
because
i think it's important that people can
um
understand what's being said and also i
think
sometimes if there is a complicated
presentation
sometimes people think so a person in
the audience might think that they are
too stupid to understand what's what the
topic is and it
it's not the case at all um it is the
responsibility of the person presenting
to make sure that
their message is clear and um and i
think
i have presented in the past when you
see people
it's really nice to see when people get
it
whilst you're presenting they understand
what you're talking about
and then i also get good feedback
afterwards because people
say that they really liked how i did
this thing or
i made it understandable and they never
realized
that two things were linked in the way
that i explained them
um and and i think getting
good feedback from people is kind of um
always a good motivation to continue i
love how you talked about
that it's um the responsibility of the
presenter to make
people understand what you're talking
about and i also feel so important
because what you have
observed i've also seen you know people
obviously don't know what you're talking
about but they don't ask
because the problem is aggravated
because nobody seems to really
understands but nobody wants to be the
first to ask a question so you have
these bad presentations and you have the
audience that just sits there and stares
at you and um
yeah this is something we definitely
need to address and i think
what you do also helps um people feel
more comfortable
with actually being in that field
because they you know this moment where
you understand something is the moment
where you feel you can do it too
you know so yeah thank you for for
looking at this this issue
um so you
had a kind of um common path into i.t
being a natural scientist and and then
moving into i.t
but if you were a young woman and you
were starting out now
to to get um on this career journey what
would you want what would you have
wanted to know at the beginning or what
recommendations would you give to a
young woman starting out
or a girl in school this is
interesting um so one thing
you mentioned a girl in school and that
reminds me
of kind of a reason i think my path was
a bit
like not direct and zigzagged because in
the uk
you can you choose you study 11 subjects
up until the age of 16 and then you only
study four
from 16 to 18 and then
um and then at university you generally
just study one
and um what's more the 11 subjects that
you choose
to finish when you're 16 you choose them
when you're 13.
so there is really really narrow
in terms of what you can study um
because yeah pretty much if you don't
study
if you don't choose to study geography
when you are 13 years old you cannot
study it at university which is crazy
because you're 13 years old how do you
know um
so um
one one interesting thing when i was
thinking about
um what i chose to study
is that i when i was 13 i chose to study
french and then when i was
16 i chose to continue studying french
and
then actually i ended up in montreal
where my french got really
good and then it was the first time i
was actually in france which
was after i was in montreal because i'd
never been to france before
um but i just think and
i just say that because i studied french
because
i liked it not because i was the best at
it but because i'd like to end
and that kind of led me to montreal and
then
kind of led me where i am now so i
really
i really think you should study what you
want to study
you study not it's not always
about studying what you are the best at
but study
what is fun i think that's really
important
um and um yeah and
i i think i was very fortunate
looking back because i didn't have
anybody who directly told me to my face
that i couldn't do something
yeah and that doesn't mean that
representation isn't important because i
never aspired to be
many things because i just didn't know
they existed but i was very fortunate
that i didn't have people around me who
were
too insecure in themselves and then
decided to try and limit my
possibilities because of this
um but i think now in
in the digital age so that there is a
lot more
so many more resources on the internet
and so many
websites you can read that people where
people create blogs and stuff like this
i would definitely give the advice to a
younger person that
um if you want to do something
um you can look into it you can find the
people
online you can find the websites online
to
to learn different things and to know to
learn different tips
and i think that's definitely um the way
to go is to do what is
is fun and do what you want very true
thank you you touched on
on one very specific thing in the
beginning which i also find
detrimental to to young people is
limiting
you know their exposure to certain
topics and information
so i feel one thing we should look at
and that's obviously not ours
a thing to do but definitely the
education system should be as broad as
possible so everybody gets a chance to
to dabble in different topics and look
at them
because obviously 13 years is much too
young to actually decide whether you
will like something
in the future or not i actually when i
was 13 i i chose german
i i chose i think i chose french
no when i was 12 i could choose between
german and spanish and i chose german
because then i got to visit germany
and then when i was 13 i decided to go
for french but now i'm fluent in both so
um it worked its way out yeah
luckily yeah but you never know right
where life will take you if it will
exactly french or something completely
different that will be useful you know
and then the second thing that makes me
thoughtful is that you said you were
lucky because nobody discouraged you
from doing what you're doing and the
same is true for me and that is probably
the reason why i
was able to go the path i did but
that's a sad thing actually you know
that you have to be happy
that at least nobody said don't do it
you're not good enough
yeah you didn't and you did don't have
the role models and you don't have the
you know the
the lift that you might need to go
higher places
i think that's something we can do for
others you know
telling them that they are definitely
good you know good enough
to choose a career in i.t or in science
and they will make it so that's
something i
i feel we should all try to do and
thank you for coming on my interview
thank you for taking the time it was
lovely just chatting with you
thank you and goodbye thank you bye
you